# Dewan Ziaul Karim

House: 23/A, Road: 1, PC Culture Housing Society, Adabor, Dhaka, Bangladesh.
Phone: +8801670206000 | Email: ziaul1891@gmail.com
Google Scholar | Github

# RESEARCH INTERESTS

My research interest lies in the domain of artificial intelligence, machine learning and software engineering. I believe that merging efficient machine learning techniques with software engineering can help developers to build error free codes which will eventually increase the productivity of the developers. I intend to utilize my engineering cognition and knowledge to develop something useful and efficient that will make a mark in future generation of engineering.

#### **EDUCATION**

# B.Sc. in Computer Science and Engineering

2012 - 2016

Thesis: Integrating Related XML Data into Data Warehouse Schema

Ahsanullah University of Science and Technology, Dhaka, Bangladesh.

CGPA: 3.91/4.00

## Higher Secondary Certificate, 12th Grade National Examination

2011

Dhaka Residential Model College, Dhaka, Bangladesh.

GPA: 5.00/5.00

## Higher Secondary Certificate, 10th Grade National Examination

2009

Dhaka Residential Model College, Dhaka, Bangladesh.

GPA: 5.00/5.00

#### Publications

- 1. Md. Afif Al Mamun, **Dewan Ziaul Karim**, Subroto Nag Pinku, Tasfia Anika Bushra, "TLNet: A Deep CNN model for Prediction of Tomato Leaf Diseases", accepted and waiting to be published in IEEE 23rd International Conference of Computer and Information Technology (ICCIT), December, 2020.
- 2. Md. Al-Amin, **Dewan Ziaul Karim**, Tasfia Anika Bushra, "Prediction of Rice Disease from Leaves using Deep Convolution Neural Network towards a Digital Agricultural System", in IEEE 22nd International Conference of Computer and Information Technology (ICCIT), December, 2019. [Paper Link]
- 3. Nafis Neehal, **Dewan Ziaul Karim**, Sejuti Banik, Tasfia Anika, "Runtime Optimization of Identification Event in ECG Based Biometric Authentication", in IEEE International Conference on Electrical, Computer and Communication Engineering (ECCE), February 2019. [Paper Link]
- 4. Nafis Neehal, **Dewan Ziaul Karim**, Ashraful Islam, "Cloud-POA: A cloud-based map only implementation of PO-MSA on Amazon multi-node EC2 Hadoop Cluster", in IEEE 20th International Conference of Computer and Information Technology (ICCIT), December 2017. [Paper Link]

#### WORK EXPERIENCE

#### Lecturer (Full Time)

May 2018 – Present

Department of Computer Science and Engineering, BRAC University, Dhaka, Bangladesh.

• Courses Taught: Introduction to Computer Science, Digital Logic Design, Data Communications, Software Engineering, System Analysis and Design.

#### Lecturer (Full Time)

September 2016 - April 2018

Department of Computer Science and Engineering,

Daffodil International University, Dhaka, Bangladesh.

• Courses Taught: Microprocessor & Assembly Language, Computer Architecture & Organization, Data Communication, Web Engineering, Social & Professional Issues in Computing, Communication Engineering.

Department of Computer Science and Engineering,

Ahsanullah University of Science and Technology, Dhaka, Bangladesh.

• Courses Taught: Computer Fundamentals, Programming Language.

#### ACHIEVEMENTS

- Dean's List of Honor award for academic excellence in Ahsanullah University of Science & Technology (2016).
- Honorable mention at Ideas for Action(I4A 2019) [Title: E- Vigilante, [page-105].
- <u>Certificate</u> in Recognition for Scopus Indexed Publication awarded by Daffodil International University (2018).
- Scholarship in Secondary School Certificate Examination from Ministry of Education, Bangladesh (2009).

### **PROJECTS**

- <u>3d Model of London Tower Bridge</u> (Language: C) A 3d model of london tower bridge built using FreeGLUT.
- Student ID Number Recognizer (Language: Matlab, Platform: Windows) An application that detects the student ID number from the image of an ID card.
- Student Information System (Language: C#, SQL, Platform: Windows) A software to manage information about students of an institution.
- Employee Information System (Language: C#, SQL, Platform: Windows) A windows application to manage information about employees of an institution.
- Snake "The Hungry Shaap" (Language: C, Platform: Windows) A simple snake game.
- Line Follower Robot with Obstacle Avoider A robot which follows a line while avoiding obstacles on its way.
- <u>Kivabejaben.com</u> (Platform: Web, Front-End: HTML,CSS, Back-End: PHP, MySQL) Website that helps users to find suitable bus routes in Bangladesh.
- <u>MovieMania.com</u> (Platform: Web, Front-End: HTML,CSS, Back-End: PHP, MySQL) Website that helps users to find information about movies.
- ColorZone (Language: Java, Platform: Android) An android drawing application.
- Fool The Alligator Game (Platform: Windows, Game Engine: Construct 2) A game where a tortoise tries to survive by escaping from alligators.
- The Hungry Monkey Game (Platform: Windows, Game Engine: Construct 2) A game where a monkey needs to eat foods while avoiding bombs.

#### Training, Conferences and Workshops

- Attended "Remote Training Program on ITEE Training of Trainers (TOT)" arranged by Bangladesh Computer Council (BCC) and AOTS, Dhaka, Bangladesh (2021).
- Participated as an author in IEEE ICCIT 2020 (Ahsanullah University of Science and Technology), ICCIT 2019 (Southeast University), ECCE 2019 (Chittagong University of Engineering & Technology (CUET) and ICCIT 2017 (University of Asia Pacific).
- Attended the workshop on "Skills Development of ICT Engineers on IT Engineers Exam (ITEE) Targeting Japanese Market" arranged by University Grants Commission (UGC), Dhaka, Bangladesh (2019).
- Completed training on CCNA Routing & Switching by American International University-Bangladesh (2016).

#### SKILLS

- Programming Language: C, Java, Python, HTML, CSS, PHP, JavaScript.
- Database: MySQL, SQL Server, Oracle.
- IDEs: Microsoft Visual Studio, NetBeans, Eclipse, Codeblocks, Proteus, emu8086, Spyder.

# LANGUAGE PROFICIENCY

• Bengali: Native

• English: IELTS: 8, CEFR level-C1

### References

# • Prof. Dr. Mohammad Shafiul Alam

Professor and Head

Computer Science & Engineering,

Ahsanullah University of Science & Technology,

Dhaka-1208, Bangladesh.

Contact No: +8801715104101 Email: shafiul.cse@aust.edu

# • Prof. Dr. S. M. Abdullah Al-Mamun

Professor

Computer Science & Engineering,

Ahsanullah University of Science & Technology,

Dhaka-1208, Bangladesh.

Contact No: +8801912073524

Email: almamun@aust.edu